[Music]
so my name is Michael Robillard and I'm
a philosopher at the University of
Oxford and I focused mainly on the
ethics of war so in a past life prior to
my my time is a professional philosopher
I was an officer in the United States
military I was an officer with the 82nd
airborne for five years roughly I spent
eight months in Iraq in 2003 2004 as a
light infantry platoon leader and I
exited the military in 2007 and have
been doing philosophy in some capacity
ever since so at least for the last 10
years since I've been out and trying to
reintegrate back into civilian society
you know I've talked with a lot of other
veteran friends from Iraq or Afghanistan
trying to sort of make sense of what it
is that we took part in and you know how
to sort of fit back in and move past it
and I came across a book called tribe by
the war journalist Sebastian Junger
and what Younger looked at was that
there's since war - there's been a
decline in in trigger time and a combat
time for soldiers from World War two
through Korea through Vietnam through
the existing engagements in Iraq and
Afghanistan and there's been an inverse
relationship of reports of PTSD and and
psychological illness in reported in
soldiers so that seems rather
counterintuitive and what I found
younger CSIS was that when you're in a
combat scenario and you're with a
platoon and you're trusting one another
with one another look one another's
lives and you're in a context where
you're you're living and sleeping right
next to each other you're eating next to
each other you're relying on one another
for emotional support and what's outside
that bubble and outside that perimeter
is the threat of imminent danger that
that essentially mimics what would
otherwise be
a tribe in a more earlier
hunter-gatherer epoch and for the modern
mind that would have probably been one
of the closest instances ever of sort of
experiencing that type of bonding so
youngers thesis is that what's sort of
making present returning veterans so
disoriented it's not so much the amount
of horror and traumas that they're being
exposed to rather it's the sharp and
jarring transition from being in this
sort of Band of Brothers moment back
into 21st century alienating society
where we're amongst a rather thin and
consumer based society people are very
sort of atomic and individualistic in
their social relationships and it ends
up sort of being like the wolf that's
lost its pack and in so doing people
lose their sense of identity and their
sense of meaning or purpose in relation
to some sort of overarching group or
overarching project and furthermore I
would argue that I think it has bearing
on a lot of the maybe groups of young
men that are even older men that are
feeling alienated in this sort of highly
atomic post informational
post-industrial society that we're in so
not really sure what to do about that
I don't think that we need something
like war or combat or life or death
scenarios in order to be some sort of
surrogate or proxy just for men to find
solidarity or meaning or purpose in fact
I think that's I mean that that that's
the very narrative that Isis and and a
lot of extremist groups are tapping into
I'm sort of puzzling through this myself
and you know I'm hoping at least some
people would step up and begin leading
and trying to to put together these
types of things these types of groups
that that could express this sort of
mail and energy and and sense of meaning
and bonding in a way that could be
productive and build social fabric
in the absence of this I'm worried
that's one of two things will happen
either men will continue to be more sort
of alienated and feeling without a place
or that energy that could be co-opted by
more pernicious groups with a lot worse
agendas I would end by saying that the
scenario that I've described or the
state of affairs that are described I
don't think it's endemic to soldiers I
don't think it's just endemic to men I
think it's endemic to really the post
21st century person and what we really
need to look at is our conception of the
individual not as some sort of atomic
entity the cleaved from all culture
cleaved from all history or cleave from
all relations so I really understand the
individual is still important
withstanding as in relation to a context
to a family to friends to a history to
it sort of social set of relations as
opposed to this sort of Cartesian atomic
individual that is not grounded in
anything bigger than itself that's all I
get my name is David fuller I'm a
journalist
and I've recently started teaching men's
work and this is a bit of a story about
how I got into men's work what I got out
of it and it's about masculinity it's
about my relationship with my father
it's a very personal story but I hope
that it's also in some way Universal
I've told it to people in the past it's
sort of yeah it seems to connect with
something quite deep in the experience
of having a father and maybe not getting
on so well with your father and then
trying to rebuild that light that that
relationship and in the later years of
your life so we're going to pull back
and start this story back in 2011 in
Libya I used to be a foreign producer
with channel 4 news Tripoli was falling
Gaddafi was on the run we came into
Tripoli just as Gaddafi's regime was
crumbling
so there's guns going off people firing
their this is center of Tripoli just as
everything's going so yeah then so
shortly after that we got to get out
Gaddafi's tent this is the burnt-out
Gaddafi's tent in the center of Tripoli
and around us all of these guns are
going off people firing into the air
it's just this incredible moment there's
a few times in my journalistic career or
I felt I'm in the middle of history this
is just an extraordinary place an
extraordinary experience and we had a
satellite phone I thought I really want
to share this so I called my parents
called my mom and she answered the phone
and I said listen listen to this just
crazy crazy moment guns going off
everywhere and she started crying and I
said okay I'm not in danger and she then
said I'm at the hospital with your dad
he's just been diagnosed with stomach
cancer and we don't know much but we
know that stomach cancer is is a
diagnosis of stomach cancer usually
means it's pretty advanced and we think
it's pretty bad and he he was young he
was fit he'd just been on cycling
holiday the literally just the week
before and so it's completely unexpected
completely out of the blue and I knew it
wasn't good I started crying as well on
the phone and my bosses at Channel 4
News thankfully just put me on a plane
straight back to to the UK and so as
we're in the plane going back to the UK
I'm just going to take a little
digression and fill in the gaps because
growing up I didn't get on well with my
father at all we always fought and we
still didn't get on even in 2011 just
before this happened and I to be honest
I was I was a bit of a little shit to
him growing up I used to kind of take
the piss out of him I used to there was
a sort of conspiracy with my mother
against him
and I was I I never worked this out
worked out why for a long time but I was
really nasty to him and I push him I
push him I push it and I I remember one
time I pushed him so much that he
grabbed me by my throat and held me up
against the wall and it didn't it didn't
sort of dawn on me until later and there
was kind of a real sense of euphoria
when I got when that happened as well it
never dawned on me until later why that
had happened it took me quite a long
time to work it out and a lot of it was
through the kind of the men's work and
the inner work that I'd done after that
that I sort of started to make sense of
it so my parents were very left-wing
very idealistic my childhood was like
CND marchers delivering leaflets for the
Labour Party they were very rebellious
as well and naturism now for about the
next couple of minutes I'm gonna be
speaking with a picture of my naked
father behind me but it's what he would
have wanted so my father was very much a
kind of new man he wanted to be very
different from the male role models that
he had and he wanted to kind of yeah be
non-competitive and be be someone
different from from his father and what
he'd seen growing up very non competitor
when we were played when we played
football me and my brother he'd say why
do you have to have a goal I can't just
pass it to each other
and it took me a while but underneath he
was he was really opinionated he was
really stubborn he always thought he was
right very different from me everybody
knows he lies and he could also get
really really angry and want his own way
and I think that's what I was doing when
I pushed him just sort of pushing that
point like to say I know that that's not
that that's not authentic that kind of
non competitive edge there's something
more there and I pushed him until he
until he snapped until I found it and my
mum told me later on that just that
moment really traumatized him like him
really it took him a long time to get
over that that that I pushed him to that
point that he grabbed me and that he
realized that he had that in him and it
took it took a lot a lot of sort of
transformational work after that where I
started to really unpack the the anger
that I had towards my father and to
really kind of understand it and and
recognize that all the things that I
disliked in him I I had it I had all of
those things in myself and was really
able to kind of understand the shadow of
what what I was pushing out in him was
something that I also had because my my
experience of men's work is that I can
speak for myself as a man I have those
those edges I have that aggression I
have that wanting to be right I have
that wanting to dominate I have all of
these things that can come out and my
experience is it's only through fully
recognizing those and integrating them
that I've become more whole as a man to
to do what you could call the shadow
work of really kind of looking at myself
really deeply and then taking that anger
taking that aggression and using it
integrating it into the personality and
then becoming sort of more more present
more powerful it becomes I think once
integrated a form of sort of personal
power and becomes a kind of fuel for
certainly to become a kind of fuel for
my life and over probably since about
2006 when I first started doing
workshops and starting doing this work
this sort of in a work from a place of
crisis in myself that I started to
really kind of integrate some of these
things and on some level I started to
heal at least some of the relationship
with him in my
although at this point we haven't kind
of healed it in the in the outside world
so planes now about to land in in the UK
and I go straight down to Southampton to
see my dad in the hospital and he's
outside in the garden with my mom and a
family friend and I just go up to him
and I embrace him and for my friend
after a few minutes my friend takes this
picture which is one of the most
precious things I have in my life I
think how probably lasted for about 10
minutes it might have been even more
sort of time stopped and my friend
realized at some point that he was in
the presence of something special and
got his phone out and took this picture
and something something I think very
profound happened in that moment some
kind of healing happens and I've had a
few friends who've looked at this a
friend of mine touched it up and has
turned it into a picture I having my
wall at home and there's something about
the way he's kind of collapsing into me
and I'm holding him that's a kind of a
transfer of some kind of I don't know as
a child taking something and taking it
from my father that that from what then
happened I feel that that's what
happened in that moment and I think what
happened here catalyzed a lot of what
happened next
because shortly after that he got the
diagnosis and he was diagnosed with
three months to live and that makes
makes things real obviously and I I then
wrote him a letter and I said I said
look I've been doing all of this work
I've done all these workshops and I get
these reflections from people in these
workshops what people say they talk
about my authenticity or they talk about
my honesty or and I realize these are
your qualities I realized that I got
them from you and I've never been able
to admit that to you
I've never been able to to recognize all
the good that I got from you
and he was very touched by that letter
and then I thought well this is he's
gonna be dead in three months why
doesn't everyone I don't want to hear
it's funeral stuff that people should
have said to him before so I then got in
touch with all of his friends all of the
family everyone that used to work with
as many people as I could and said he's
gonna be dead in three months I want to
hit I want you to what you might want to
say at the funeral I want you to say it
now and send it to him and so over the
next three months as he was becoming
more and more ill lying in bed my mum
was reading these to him and all of this
amazing stuff started coming in from
former friends work colleagues family so
he was an arts officer for the council
and created the Southampton Film
Festival save the Theatre Royal in
Winchester created the street parties in
the road and my father's like core wound
was that he really didn't think he'd
achieved very much in his life he he had
a real down on himself and felt that
he'd been a failure he'd never read a
amounted to much and this this has
really eaten away at him and then
somehow in the last three months of his
life some of that change some of that
shift of just from the weight of all
this stuff coming in and the sheer love
an outpouring of stuff that came in and
I write I'm sure that part of that was
catalyzed by that one moment and that
one healing I was able to do and then to
be there for him and then to produce I
turned him yeah I'm sure it was
catalyzed by this by this moment and
then I I made a I took all of those and
made it into a book that I gave to him
for his for his birthday sort of about
three weeks before he died because there
was also when when things like this
happen there's there's a Jordan Peterson
quote where he talks about be the person
to rely on in a funeral it's hard enough
in a funeral but it can be absolute hell
if you haven't dealt with your family
stuff and I really feel because all
sorts of stuff came in some people are
in denial some people are in don't want
to know I mean other members of my
family just wanted it to go away they
weren't ready for I feel that I I was
able to be there because of the work
that I'd done and yeah it turned into a
really beautiful experience rather than
being absolute hell even though we were
all there when he died we we were
holding hands around his bed when he
died and it was it was very yeah it was
it was one of the most I now look back
on it it's one of the most precious
moments of my life and it's a it's a
wonderful it's a it's a wonderful story
and it's often I told this sort of over
the last few years and this is normally
where it ends and it's but it's not
where it ends because as someone who had
I believed my father's image of himself
like I I treated him as this failure
growing up I'd realized that I didn't
turn alized the story that he hadn't
treated him the same way to kind of
treated himself and then to have all of
this come on at the age of 36 to realize
by the time he was my age he'd opened at
Art Center he saved a theater he'd
created the Southampton Film Festival he
had three kids it's like oh this guy I
thought was a failure at a chief farm or
that that stage that I had and there's
also something that in my experience
when your father goes as a man that's
there's something archetypal even though
I didn't get on that well my father
there's something there that's missing
this sort of archetypal grounding point
and I really found that I had to go on a
journey of myself over the next sort of
six months to really find my path and
find what I needed to do and it was it
then became like the hardest period of
my life like I had some real ups and
downs over the last six years just
really trying to get my shit together
and decide what it was that was meant to
be doing with my life and what I was
meant to be bringing into the world yeah
it was pretty hard
and yeah it's only in the last year I
feel that I've really started to come
out of that and realize what it is that
I'm supposed to be doing and it's sort
of its leading men's work use my
journalistic skills to tell the stories
of this kind of transformational work
and then to lead the work because you
can only you can't you can't show
someone a film and give them a
transformational experience you've got
to give the transformational experience
as well and this is the work that I'm
most passionate about and this is what I
found the most helpful in my in my
personal journey and we consciously in
our workshops we consciously bring in
support of the father it's a very kind
of emotional piece for a lot of men to
to feel that to model some up some
healthy father energy in that workshop
space and we had a guy a father and our
last workshop who said he he really
wanted to go away and give that to his
son so I you know as always writing this
yesterday kind of I wish that my father
had had some of this and maybe the
relationship that I have with him would
have been a bit different but he did the
best he could and I'm really grateful
for that and I just want to yea honor
him by raising a toast to Michael -
Michael
it's not representing the organization a
band of brothers we few we happy few we
band of brothers for he today who sheds
his blood with me shall be my brother be
he ne'er so vile this day shall gentle
his condition Shakespeare's Henry v and
that's the inspiration for for the name
of our charity that started about a
decade ago and we were sat in a loft and
there was a group of us about sort of
seventeen eighteen of us and we'd all
been doing the type of men's work that
David was describing that process of
really looking at Who am I what should I
do with my life and it is there any
meaning and purpose and we've been doing
this work for about four or five years
and we felt a huge amount better about
ourselves but as we sat there in that
loft in Hove we realized that if if
there is a crisis in masculinity it
wasn't really amongst us because we were
pretty white pretty middle-class and
pretty privileged and that maybe just
maybe if we were to set about trying to
do something to address some problems
that we saw in society where we should
be focusing our efforts was in the
council estates where we knew that young
men were leaving care going into the
prison system getting locked up
returning from the prison system more
damaged and fucked up than they were
when they went in and what would it be
like for us to set ourselves the
challenge of reaching out a hand to them
going back to the ancient ancient
traditions of the older men in a society
believing it to be their responsibility
their sacred charge to initiate the
younger men to say to the younger men
this is how we do stuff around here this
is what we expect from you
and in return this is what you can
expect from us it's not a one-way street
being a man in this tribe and we
believed that that that that social
contract that bond had been lost and
what would it be like if we try to
recreate that so that was ten years ago
and what I'm going to do now is show you
and allow you to hear the voices of some
of the young men and some of the
volunteers that we've worked with over
the past decade and then I'm going to
return and talk a bit about what we've
learned in the ten years that we've been
doing this work well if you think about
communities in the safety of communities
they're most sort of at risk through
unsocialized young men I remember seeing
my dad going down the road from his
house when he had passed and I was there
and I'm bogged down about it I got put
in the cell and I said I'll never do it
again then I got done it again and I
ended up back in the cell I don't work
at a to become man it's just one of them
things we as a community of men
recognized that all of us are wounded
all of us have our own issues all of us
are struggling to answer the big
questions of life of Who am I really
what should I do with my life and is
there really any meaning or purpose and
we engage in those questions with the
young men but I'm living the new life
that I always wanted to live
[Applause]
so what we do is we take young men
referrals from the Probation Service and
we approach them and we offer them the
call to adventure do you want to come
and see what what maybe is behind and
driving what what what what your life
looks like and those young men have
often never had an invitation quite like
that we take them away to the woods we
take them off to the woods
we take them away from their known world
and surrounding those 10 or 12 men on
those rites of passage weekends are
twenty five grown men from their
community we set out with a belief and a
hypothesis that what the young men were
looking for was meaning purpose and
belonging meaning purpose and belonging
and that was certainly borne out and for
too many men in this country there is an
absence of meaning purpose and belonging
what we didn't realize when we started
doing this was how much our older male
volunteers were also in desperately in
need of meaning purpose and belonging
and that bringing those two groups
together has been deeply deeply healing
because instinctively I felt scared of
young men I still notice it come up in
me occasionally even now even after
doing this work for years and years I
walk past a group of males in hoodies at
a bus bus stop and part of me will feel
scared and yet now chances are I might
know one of them
another thing that we're we're seeing is
that one of the jewels spoke earlier
about the stiff upper lip the kind of
the traditions of the upper-class
Englishmen that started perhaps with
that sentiment of the definition of a
boor is an Englishman who when you ask
him how he is he actually tells you so
that there's that kind of thing that and
that we heard about that boarding school
of environment of never showing any fear
and you know what it's the same for the
young men growing up on the council
estates going to the going to prisons
like being in those environments they
are not the only emotion that they can
show is anger grief and sadness no fear
no like love and joy no so their
emotional range a lot of the emotional
range of men and young men gets
channeled into a very very narrow funnel
so we see that the work that we're doing
in allowing men and young men to improve
their emotional literacy to express the
grief the sadness the shame that fear
that might have been inside them for
years without finding ground we believe
is really really important the other
thing that we're finding is that men
need community and I used to say to
funders and people that came down to see
our work I used to tell them that this
is my community this isn't just a youth
project this is my community these men
in this community will bury me when I go
and that was always a kind of it was a
it was a construct but last year what
happened is that one of those men that
was sat in that room with us in Hove ten
years ago died I'll bring his name here
tonight Peter and Peter died and we as a
community held held that process held
his
you know the young men the young man
that he first mentored went up to the
woodland burial site and was part of a
group of men digging the grave that
would hold that man telling stories of
what they remembered and what they
celebrated about Peter Wow
that sent ripples right through our
community knowing that that's how we
look after each other that's how we look
after our own so whilst we're creating
social good we're also getting a huge
amount of value for ourselves and that
for me is what what service really looks
like and I'll leave you there thank you
very much
what's the value of having groups of
just men because some of what you're
talking about is kind of sharing and
vulnerability in that that can happen in
different kinds of groups can it so what
is the value of doing it with just men
there's two parts to it really one is
that what will happen in in Akko gender
group is that as a heterosexual man I
will start to try and establish some
rank because I'll be aware of aware of
which of the women that I want to sleep
with and I want to look good and that
will mean that I'm showing up in a
different way too if I wasn't doing that
and I feel quite embarrassed admitting
to this but that's how it works and
there's also something that's a bit kind
of subtler than that which is that what
I do Co gender work I think there is
absolutely a place for doing Co gender
work especially in the times of me - I
believe there is a massive need for men
and women to hear each other's stories
going beyond the stereotypes beyond all
of the kind of stuff I think there's
absolute you need for that and what can
sometimes happen in Co gender groups is
that I will expect
unconsciously the men will expect the
women in the group to do the
stereotypically feminine emotions so the
men will expect the women to hold the
vulnerability the sadness the grief and
and and it can become polarizing whereas
when it's an all-male group we find
ourselves manifesting and experiencing
those emotions demonstrating them
modeling for the young men that we can
be in an authentic space of masculinity
and in those emotions and you know at
the weekend we do all of that stuff
that's traditionally seen as in our
polarized gendered society is being
feminine so we cook and we clean and we
look after the young men and we'd clear
their plates and we do all of that stuff
because they've often never experienced
being nurtured by by other men and often
they don't don't see they don't honor
that part within themselves so that's
kind of why we why we do it as a single
gender groups yeah it's a really good
question and I would say there's a
couple of things I completely agree with
with Nathan that when a woman enters the
room men's behavior changes it's just
it's just something that happens on a
very subtle level and performance comes
in or whatever it's a there's an element
of inauthenticity that can come in very
easily but also I think there is
something that we can give to each other
as men that that really feeds us on a on
a deep level someone's called it the
vitamin M that we're all craving for on
some level and I've this is a really
bodily ID I think you probably agree
there's a bodily experience of some kind
of sustenance that comes in I'm sure is
related to kind of this deep
evolutionary history of being around men
and doing things together with men and
it's a real felt sense it's like you
don't know that you're missing this but
you are and and that that really comes
in I think in that in that space it's
like I'm on a much deeper level we knew
when we started doing this well we had a
suspicion that the young men would
really value an older man blessing them
looking them in the eyes and going what
I see in you young man is a fine soul
somebody who really cares about those
around them has somebody who this you
know so it's a really blessing them and
we were absolutely spot on in that and
that means a huge amount to the young
men what we didn't realize was how much
we as older men were craving the
blessing of the younger men for them to
say to us
chi noir nobody's ever cared about me
and you lot have thank you it was just
like wow like that that just meant so
much and and and and we didn't see that
coming
I would certainly very much like to hear
from some of the women in the room about
what their feelings are listening to
some of the stories that have been
shared or yeah some of the experiences
or what what's come up for them in terms
of hearing some of the things that been
shared tonight I would like to say that
I have really appreciated that you guys
don't have a front today I really feel
that what you have said has come from
you personally and I think that is what
a lot of women are missing out on
frankly when they're talking to men in
talk to a boss talk to colleague we
don't try and see behind your fronts and
I really appreciate today that you guys
have been personal and honest and you've
trusted that people have listened to you
without judgment and I think that's I
really appreciate that as a woman
listening to this to you guys today
and the reason why I came here today is
to see whether whether or not there's
anything women can do to support men to
help them have a more positive healthier
kind of version of masculinity or
whether we should just like step back do
you know what I mean so I wanted to hear
from men and I guess I would like to
hear maybe from you guys what you think
on that
what met what women can do to support
this I suppose I mean what I'd say for
myself is that through really connecting
to my masculinity and the work has
really enabled me to connect with the
women in my life I mean the kind of the
terminology is to connect with the
feminine like connection to my Maskin
has allowed me really to connect with
the feminine and I feel that's in myself
as well as outside it's it's rooting
myself really into my masculine has
really allowed me to connect with my own
in a feminine and then with with the
women in my life so that but I think
there is something that we have to do
for ourselves yeah in terms of kind of
growing out of my toxic model of
masculinity of my early 20s the
friendship of women was so crucial to
that I mean I would say even now I
probably got more close female friends
the male because it was just easier to
have authentic you know conversations
with them but I think that David's right
that it can't be just that I mean I
think I still have issues around
trusting men and and opening up with men
and so there is I I kind of been
converted by these guys to the idea
there is there is some good work to be
done you know with I'd have never been
to a men's group but I mean I'm more
open to the idea yeah this that there is
that there is a kind of healing in terms
of trusting other men as well I made a
really bad mistake which was a female
friend of mine and I were talking about
the me to stuff
and she said to me you men all have a
problem you need to sort this out and I
was just like huh
you wouldn't approach a person of Muslim
faith and say do you Muslims have got a
real problem with like you know kind of
extremism in your community you all need
to sort it out so what why do you think
that all men are responsible for the
actions of extremists like Harvey
Weinstein within our community that's
not to say that we don't have issues
around sex and stuff that we need to
work through but there is something in
that because what I missed in that was
the opportunity to say to her because
what she went on to disclose was the
actually she being a sexually assaulted
when she was younger and that still
carried a lot of stuff around it and
because of how the conversation had gone
I didn't get to say to her I that was
wrong and I'm sorry that that happened
and I didn't get to grieve with her for
what was lost in the moment because I
was too in my own reaction around like
all of you men and carrying the burden
and the shame of all of that collective
stuff so yeah that would be the other
thing I've turned a more serious no to
you know for all of us as human beings
to look when we're generalizing and one
we're giving somebody stuff that isn't
theirs - one yep essentially one for you
David and I was really moved by your
story and I was wondering if you have
any ideas or thoughts about how that
sort of approach Minh or how that
changing that relation can happen before
before it gets at that stage as it were
and because I think many people would
rather it is often left to that that
lateness isn't it and that actually you
won't see it before now I have tried to
do this my own father had that sort of
deep in musical conversation I think you
just found it bit awkward and weird and
wasn't really willing to go there and
for me it would seem a shame to leave it
to that same stage when it's so so late
in the day yeah very good question yeah
I wish it hadn't been sparked by that
and by that shortened timespan and made
it all more intense
there's only so much you can do you can
only offer you can't you can't change
the way it's received there's a there's
a course that I did once that said and
it was about kind of healing with your
parents and what they said is open the
conversation by saying I love you and I
know that you've always loved me and
that that recognition of of their their
love was that was the thing that would
open the door and it worked I think I
said it's my mom she said I know but I'd
already said that to my dad and it
hadn't kind of it haven't fixed the
relationship so there's often there's
always more work to do in ourselves as
well there's often stuff that it's like
we it's difficult to know whether it's
really coming from a resolve place in
ourselves and then whether we can we can
actually come from that that place of
healing my relationship improved a lot
with my dad when I was in a really bad
accident
so we bonded through that any major
injury yeah on this one I feel because I
have such a great relationship with my
dad I mean we have some incredibly deep
conversations about the weather and
what's gonna happen in the next 48 hours
meteor odd meteor logically and you know
what he's just not ready for those
conversations anything deeper and you
know what I've come to to accept is is a
couple of things really one is that we
all want a Superman for for our fathers
and what we get is a human being and
that's so that's that you know some
stuff to work through and the other the
other thing for me as well is to accept
that like my dad's dad went off to war
in the second world war came back
couldn't really speak about it didn't
ever speak about it
didn't ever really parent my dad and so
he is who he is and I ended up who I am
and that perhaps our generation of the
ones with the tools that we used to just
gently
try and unlock every now and again but
wait if it's right and hopefully it
won't be the three months to go stage
that David was yeah I think it's pretty
difficult to create a relationship that
he doesn't have anywhere else in his
life
like it's very difficult to create a
closer relationship than any of the
other relationships that that someone
has that's very difficult and I want to
ask you about Superman this word came up
thanks all of you for sharing such
swords being so courageous I'm gonna use
that word being vulnerable and sharing a
little bit of your own honest truths and
stories that's really moved me and being
something quite powerful to encounter
I guess I'm interested to ask you
personally as as men fellow men what you
do about your urge to fix the world or
to try and be a Superman to solve things
to have the answer to build a program
that's gonna be you know the thing and
maybe this is a kind of a man problem I
don't know or is it okay how do you feel
about that I have had that I definitely
see it in my brother as well young
called it like the archetype of the
eternal boy like the golden child who
were kind of on a mission to save the
world and and men can be very into hero
archetypes and personal development can
really draw on that as well like you go
on a hero's journey and so forth and I
still feel it in me sometimes as well
you know what am I going to do to set
the world on fire and I guess one thing
I can do is recognize that sometimes the
real work is accepting yourself when you
haven't done something amazing and
you're not on some massive mission so
that can be the hardest work when you're
not kind of caffeined up and thinking ah
this this is going to be the thing you
know
so yeah I think just recognizing that
tendency in oneself and then it can be a
form of unkindness to one because you
know like Who am I when I'm not a
superhero when I'm when I'm not being
amazing and can I accept myself in that
is I think really hard work yeah I guess
um
you know so I guess by now a lot of
people are familiar with the the Jordan
Peterson meme of clean up clean up your
room and sort of this this notion of
having starting small and and becoming
responsible for one's own sort of inner
world and and local space and without
getting overwhelmed by trying to solve
all the world's problems with some one
utopian grand plan you know so I think
that there's there's definitely in
elements and a sentiment to that that
makes a lot of sense so trying to fix
the world has nearly killed me on
several occasions and fortunately I've
now come to a place with it
where I'd still like to fix the world if
I'm honest but I won't consider myself a
failure if I don't manage to do it and
that for me it feels like a real
position to be in and so for me there's
this kind of balance of not abdicating
but also not overreaching and not
projecting my own psychological fuck-ups
onto external forces and going out and
campaigning with that and I think that's
really what Jordan Peters is saying like
you know don't project your wounds and
vulnerabilities out there into the world
and concentrate on that fix that stuff
first once you got far enough with that
to not be a liability putting yourself
out there crack on get on with it go do
it so that's kind of my work-in-progress
around it so I work with young people
with a charity called mind and my job is
in service design currently so I'm
looking at how can we help young people
in schools and reimagine mental health
support for young people in schools so I
spent the last sort of six weeks running
focused group
of young people and if the young people
aren't forced to be there then it will
always be girls if they're cherry in
life they're cherry pick then you can
kind of get you can get boys in the moon
as well but even when the boys are in
the room getting them to actually use
their voice and to articulate their
inner experience is incredibly difficult
and draining this has been replicated it
was every South London school that I've
been in it's the same thing if the boy
is not speaking up you've had some of
these huge campaigns like time to change
that's taken on mental health stigma for
example from a seemingly unassailable
position and beaten it down to a point
where it's kind of okay to say I'm
struggling now much more so than before
and I'm curious to know our funders our
governments do you see it on the horizon
that this stuff is actually going to be
looked at that perhaps it might be a
good idea to start tackling this problem
a little bit further upstream rather
than waiting to the young people burn
the village down just to feel the warmth
how long have we got it's a huge
question and I think I could go in and
pick apart lots of different bits of
that and the thing for me the piece I
think that we can do is that bit about
imagining what the healthy journey from
being a young boy to a mature adult man
looks like and rather than focus on
pathologizing the problems really focus
on what does the positive journey look
like and can we lobby for those stages
to be included within the curriculum in
schools I would say how to get them into
the room I wouldn't have gone to a
mental health voluntary workshop when I
was a teenager I might have gone to one
on ideas and philosophy you could do one
on like sports and values where you have
some kind of game and then the kind of
discussion afterwards or something like
music and then some discussion
afterwards so come at it sideways rather
than straight on
we're gonna fix you so that's that's
supposed to I think that's a really
great idea I think it's very difficult
to reach men just by saying this will
make you more healthy or you'll be more
in touch with your emotions it's like
okay why it's like okay this will help
you get into a state for making better
music or this will help you go to the
state for making better art or or
something I mean something around that I
mean we're having this conversation as
well with with rebel wisdom we're
thinking about doing sort of martial
arts to kind of tap into come and
release your anger in a martial arts
session and then do some sharing around
it and reframe it within kind of there I
think there has to be a function beyond
just the the therapeutic benefit of it
and I think no one's cracked it yet
we're kind of talking about it as well
and I think the other thing is
mainstreaming this personal growth
conversation it has to be made
mainstream and it hasn't been yet and
that's sort of something I think we're
all like part of this evening tonight
it's kind of there's there's clearly an
appetite for it from the from the
response that there's been in the room
and yeah we're gonna wrap up now and say
thank you very much for all of you came
and are some great questions and you
have some great responses in the break
to Nathan from Band of Brothers to
Michael from the US Army and Oxford
University
and to to jewels from the London
philosophy Club and Thessaly Walker and
David rebel wisdom thank you very much
you